All right, בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody, today's דף daf is מ"ד
Mem Dalet 44. We pick up on the bottom third of מ"ג
עמוד ב. Mem Gimmel Amud Bet. We're in the middle of discussions
about כופר. kofer. We just had a nice lovely long discussion about
whether there is כופר kofer or שלשים של עבד shloshim shel eved
paid when there is no סקילה skila of the ox. We said
that somewhat ironically there's more of a weight to say that the
שלשים של עבד shloshim shel eved is linked to the כופר. kofer.
We've seen more variations of opinions around the שלשים של עבד shloshim
shel eved is linked to the סקילה, skila, to the stoning of
the ox. We've seen a more variety of opinions around whether the
כופר kofer is linked to the stoning of the ox. And we
also saw a very important discussion about when there is no כופר
kofer or שלשים של עבד, shloshim shel eved, will there be a
fallback payment of actual תשלומין tashlumin for the life of a human
being, which you don't have when a person kills a person, but
do you have it when an ox kills a person? And then
the גמרא Gemara even asks do you have it when a fire
kills a person, is there an idea of compensation for a life?
Okay, now we pick up at the bottom third of מ"ג עמוד
ב, Mem Gimmel Amud Bet, כי אתא. ki ata. כי אתא רב
דימי אמר רבי יוחנן. Ki ata Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Yochanan. Line
starts with the word אמר רבי יוחנן. amar Rabbi Yochanan. It's about
I don't know where it is, it's about fifteen lines from the
bottom, right by the דף. daf. כי אתא רב דימי אמר רבי
יוחנן, Ki ata Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Yochanan, כופר, kofer, מה תלמוד
לומר ma talmud lomar כופר. kofer. It could have said כופר, kofer,
it says אם כופר. im kofer. מה תלמוד לומר Ma talmud lomar
אם כופר, im kofer, if a כופר kofer is placed on him.
What, there's an option you should kill the guy? Obviously you always
do a כופר. kofer. So what's the אם כופר? im kofer? לרבות
כופר שלא בכוונה ככופר בכוונה, l'rabot kofer shelo b'kavana k'kofer b'kavana, to
go against the positions that we said yesterday. This is saying to
tell you that there will even be a כופר kofer when the
ox gores unintentionally, it tried to kill an animal and killed the
human being, you're not going to stone the ox, nevertheless you're still
going to pay a כופר. kofer. כופר kofer gets paid without the
stoning of the ox. אמר ליה אביי אלא מעתה, Amar leh Abaye
ela me'ata, so if that's true, עבד נמי, eved nami, so let's
get to this question about the שלשים shloshim of the עבד eved
and the stoning. Maybe that also should also get paid without stoning
the ox, right? These are the two things we looked at yesterday.
מה תלמוד לומר Ma talmud lomar אם עבד. im eved. Let it
just say עבד יגח השור או אמה כסף שלשים שקלים. eved yigach
hashor o ama kesef shloshim shekalim. Why did it say אם? im?
אם im also seems to be an extra word. So why don't
we say the same thing? לרבות עבד שלא בכוונה כעבד בכוונה, l'rabot
eved shelo b'kavana k'eved b'kavana, that you'll pay even if it gores
the slave unintentionally. So the same way you've decoupled כופר kofer from
the stoning of the ox because of this extra word אם, im,
let's decouple the thirty shekel of the עבד eved from the stoning
of the ox and say that you'll pay the thirty shekel even
when you don't stone the ox. So the גמרא Gemara says וכי
תימא הכי נמי, v'chi teima hachi nami, and if you're going to
say so it is, okay, so pay the שלשים של עבד shloshim
shel eved without stoning the ox. והאמר ריש לקיש שור אין מיתת
עבד שלא בכוונה פטור משלשים שקלים. V'ha'amar Reish Lakish shor ein mitat
eved shelo b'kavana patur mishloshim shekalim. But
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says you don't pay that. ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish says that you don't pay the thirty shekel if you don't
stone the ox. אמר ליה, Amar leh, so he said back to
him, גברא אגברא קרמית. gavra a-gavra qaramit. Okay,
what are you doing? You're asking one person against another person? Fine,
okay, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish disagrees and I presumably would say you
pay כופר kofer without stoning the ox and you pay שלשים של
עבד shloshim shel eved without stoning the ox, challenging everything we said
yesterday. כי אתא רבין, Ki ata Ravin, that was when רב דימי
Rav Dimi came. כי אתא רבין אמר רבי יוחנן, Ki ata Ravin
amar Rabbi Yochanan, when רבין Ravin came he said in the name
of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan something he didn't say it about כופר,
kofer, he said it about the thirty of an עבד. eved. עבד,
eved, מה תלמוד לומר ma talmud lomar אם עבד. im eved. So
he said explicitly that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would decouple both of
them. לרבות עבד שלא בכוונה כעבד בכוונה, l'rabot eved shelo b'kavana k'eved
b'kavana, that you pay the thirty shekel even if you don't stone
the ox, even if the ox gores שלא בכוונה. shelo b'kavana. Okay,
so who cares, or not who cares, but whatever, but so ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish disagrees. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says the כופר kofer
isn't linked and the שלשים של עבד shloshim shel eved isn't linked.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says וריש לקיש נמי נימא מדידי עבד
אם עבד לא דריש כופר אם כופר נמי לא דריש. v'Reish Lakish
nami neima mididei eved im eved lo darish kofer im kofer nami
lo darish. And now finally the גמרא's Gemara going to explore sort
of the relation whether these two go together. If ריש לקיש's Reish
Lakish statement was only about the שלשים של עבד, shloshim shel eved,
so if the extra word אם im by the word אם עבד
im eved doesn't tell him to decouple, so maybe he would also
say should we assume for ריש לקיש Reish Lakish if the שלשים
של עבד shloshim shel eved is coupled with the stoning of the
ox, the כופר kofer is coupled with the stoning of the ox?
If you don't דריש darish the אם im in one case, you
won't דריש darish it in the other case. מדידי עבד אם עבד
לא דריש כופר אם כופר נמי לא דריש. Mididei eved im eved
lo darish kofer im kofer nami lo darish. אמרי לא, Amri lo,
no, not necessarily have to say that those two go together. עבד
אם עבד לא דריש, eved im eved lo darish, the extra אם
im by עבד eved he does not learn to decouple the two.
כופר אם כופר דריש, kofer im kofer darish, but the extra אם
im by כופר kofer he does say that that decouples. So as
opposed to yesterday where we said both כופר kofer and the שלשים
shloshim were linked to the stoning of the ox, here we're saying
that according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan neither of them is linked,
you'll always pay it separately, and according to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
maybe the שלשים של עבד shloshim shel eved is linked but the
כופר kofer is not linked. What's the difference? ומאי שנא עבד אם
עבד לא כתיב. u-mai shna eved im eved lo ktiv. מקום תשלומין.
m'kom tashlumim. Right? It says with it, if עבד, eved, oh I
erased it,
אם עבד יגח השור או אמה כסף שלושים שקלים. Im eved yigach
hashor oh amah kessef shloshim shekalim.
So when it talks about the payment, it doesn't have the word
אם. im. The word אם im is in telling you something about
the payment. Word אם im is just setting up the scenario, אם
עבד. im eved. So we're not going to use that word אם
im to tell you, oh the payment comes separate from the stoning.
Okay, so it's just just in terms of the hermeneutics, in terms
of the text. כופר אם כופר כתיב במקום תשלומין. Kofer im kofer
ksiv b'mkom tashlumim.
It says אם כופר יושת עליו im kofer yushat alov that's talking
about paying the כופר. kofer. So you have an extra word in
the place where it's talking about the payment, that's coming to tell
you something about the payment. That's coming to tell you to decouple
the two. Okay, so we have now three positions. We have that
they what the גמרא Gemara was saying yesterday, that you'll that the
both it's true that the coupling is true about both of them,
כופר kofer will only be with the stoning and שלושים של עבד
shloshim shel eved will only be with the stoning. We have the
position of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that neither of them are linked,
you can pay כופר kofer without stoning and you can pay שלושים
shloshim without stoning כופר kofer without stoning is certainly a dominant position
that we've seen. And then you have the גמרא Gemara clarifying where
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish could be a middle position. כופר kofer you'll
pay without stoning, which has been a very common position, but the
שלושים, shloshim, that's always tightly linked with the stoning, and that actually
is works well with the פסוק pasuk because the פסוק pasuk puts
it very tight. It says: כסף שלושים שקלים יתן לאדוניו והשור יסקל.
kessef shloshim shekalim yitein l'adonav v'hashor yisakel.
So the only thing that's linked is the שלושים של עבד. shloshim
shel eved. As we pointed out it's a little bit ironic, right?
Because you would think the שלושים של עבד shloshim shel eved is
more about payment of compensation, so who really cares if the ox
is חייב כופר? chayav kofer? Whereas stoning is about more of an
act of murder by the ox, and there you would think it's
more linked. So it's a little it's definitely ironic this position that
the כופר kofer isn't linked and the שלושים shloshim is. Yes.
I'm just trying to understand what the גמרא Gemara really thinks about
כופר, kofer, is it כפרה kaparah or is it ממון? mamon? Because
it seems to vacillate about... Why? Because didn't it first say like
when it asked according to I forget who it was, like רבי
ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, oh he holds that it's a כפרה kaparah whereas
everyone...
Yeah, the גמרא Gemara has it as an open question, but it
very much comes down on the side of כפרה, kaparah, very consistently.
Right, all the questions about חצי כופר ולא כופר שלם ולא חצי
כופר chatzi kofer v'lo kofer shalem v'lo chatzi kofer all those things.
The גמרא Gemara raises it as a question but it's very dominant
predominantly comes down on the side of כפרה. kaparah.
Except there is never never כופר kofer for an עבד. eved.
Correct. Okay, yeah, I mean that's whatever, that's troubling. It's troubling that
an עבד eved is completely reduced to its monetary value. Okay, וכן
בבן ובבת. v'chein b'ven u'vevat. Now we get to the next part
of the פסוק. pasuk. Right? או בן יגח או בת יגח כמשפט
הזה יעשה
לו. Oh ben yigach oh bat yigach kamishpat hazeh ye'aseh lo. Alright
and we pointed out earlier, right? The question is who needs to
say that? Right, you basically said, you gore a person this is
what you do. What you think that the life of a child
is less worthy of the הלכות halachas of כופר kofer or stoning
the ox? So we pointed out that you know, that the historians
point out that it could be a response to other law codes
in the Middle East, which basically said that if your ox gores
and kills the child of another person, then your child is killed.
So the whole point of the תורה Torah is to tell you
you don't kill the owner, you don't kill his kids, you basically
stone the ox and you pay כופר kofer if it's habitual. But
let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with it. וכן בבן וכן
בבת. v'chein b'ven v'chein b'vat. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. או בן יגח
או בת יגח. Oh ben yigach oh bat yigach. וחייב על הקטנים
כגדולים v'chayav al haktanim k'gedolim to tell me that you are just
as liable for goring minors as for goring adults. אבל לא דינו.
Aval lo dinu. That's obvious. הואיל וחיייב אדם באדם וחייב שור בשור
שור באדם. Hoil v'chiyav adam b'adam v'chiyav shor b'shor shor b'adam. If
a person kills a person, that's murder. If an ox gores a
person then we have these things, stoning and paying כופר. kofer. מה
כשחייב אדם באדם Ma k'shechiyav adam b'adam when a person kills a
person לא שנא בין קטנים לגדולים, lo shna bein ktanim l'gdolim, it
doesn't matter if you kill an adult or you kill a child,
it's still murder. אף כשחייב שור באדם Af k'shechiyav shor b'adam similarly
when an ox gores a person לא תחלק בו בין קטנים לגדולים.
lo tachlok bo bein ktanim l'gdolim. Obviously it should be treated the
same, not make a distinction. ועוד קל וחומר הוא. V'od kal v'chomer
hu. It's not only a logical comparison, it's a קל וחומר. kal
v'chomer. ומה אדם באדם שלא עשה בו קטנים כגדולים U'ma adam b'adam
shelo asa bo ktanim k'gdolim when you talk about a human doing
an act of murder. If the minor is the perpetrator is the
murderer, he's not prosecuted. So there's a way when we're talking about
murder that minors are excluded from being the perpetrator, okay? וחייב על
הקטנים כגדולים v'chayav al haktanim k'gedolim so now
even though they're excluded from being the murderer, they're not prosecuted, but
you're liable when they are the murder victim.
שור באדם שעשה בו קטנים כגדולים Shor b'adam she'asa bo ktanim k'gdolim
does it matter if the ox is a young ox, a teenage
ox or an adult ox? No. So by the ox it doesn't
matter whether the murdering ox is an adult or a minor.
אינו דין שחייב על הקטנים כגדולים? Eino din shechiyav al haktanim k'gdolim?
Certainly it should be treated the same, not make a distinction. לא,
lo, no, not necessarily, I could have had a reason to make
this a difference. אם אמרת אדם באדם Im amarta adam b'adam maybe
we'll be more weighty by a human committing murder and say that
you're חייב chayav even if the murder victim is a minor. שכן
חייב בארבעה דברים Shekein chayav b'arba devarim because we know that humans
doing acts against other humans has weightier הלכות, halachos, right? When it's
an act of injury, a personal injury, you pay... by these extra
four payments, right? נזק, צער, ריפוי, שבת, בושת. nezek, tza'ar, ripuy, shevet,
boshet. So that whole category is a more weighty category. So תאמר
בשור שאינו חייב בארבע דברים? tomar beshor she'eino chayav b'arba devarim? So
an ox where there'll never be these additional payments, maybe the Torah
would treat the when an ox kills a child, maybe it would
treat it differently. תלמוד לומר, או בן יגח או בת יגח. Talmud
lomar o ben yigach o bat yigach. Therefore, you need this extra
פסוק, pasuk, לחייב על הקטנים כגדולים, l'chayev al haktanim k'gedolim, to tell
me that it's just as much when it gores an adult as
it gores a child. Yes.
What's the difference technically between דין הוא din hu and קל וחומר
הוא? kal vachomer hu?
So sometimes דין din does mean קל וחומר, kal vachomer, but דין
din more means it's like you can, it's logical. You
should know this by pure logic.
It has to be very similar.
But it's not a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. חייב אדם וחייב שור
באדם chayav adam v'chayav shor b'adam is an analogy. It's not a
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Okay. All right. So the גמרא Gemara goes
like this.
Okay. So that's why you need the או בן יגח או בת
יגח, o ben yigach o vat yigach. because since humans against humans
is a more weighty category, maybe I could not have learned out
that we treat the goring and the killing of a child the
same way of a killing of an adult.
Okay. ואין לי אלא במועדים. v'ein li ela b'muadim. Now, that's only
by a מועד, muad, because remember we said, you know, the end
of the פסוק, pasuk, או בן יגח או בת יגח, o ben
yigach o vat yigach, the whole end there about the שלשים shloshim
of the עבד, eved, was talking about a מועד, muad, right? And
therefore presumably the goring of the kids is talking about a מועד,
muad, that you stone the ox and you pay
the
כופר kofer right
now?
No, no, no.
You don't pay the כופר. kofer. That's the killing a child is
no different than an adult. I mean, there's no weight.
מועד muad you would do the כופר kofer and the stoning. I
know, it's like a shift. But like, I know the same הלכות
halachot apply מועד muad of an adult and מועד muad of a
child. How do I know the same הלכות halachot apply תם tam
of an adult and תם tam of a child? Okay. אלא במועדים
בתם מנין? ela b'muadim b'tam minayin? דין הוא. din hu. It's to
learn it out.
הואיל וחייב באיש ואישה. ho'il v'chiyav b'ish v'ishah. Remember it says, כי
יגח שור את איש או את אשה ומת. ki yigach shor et
ish o et ishah vamat. Okay. So since it treats the goring
of a man and of a woman similarly, the whole point is
to say it doesn't matter man or woman, and that's up there
by the תם, tam, right? So the comparison of איש ואישה ish
v'ishah don't make a distinction between man and woman is up there
by a תם. tam. So the same way here it's telling you
don't make a distinction adult or child, that should also be true
by a תם tam as well. Okay. דין הוא. din hu. הואיל
וחייב באיש ואישה וחייב בבן ובת. ho'il v'chiyav b'ish v'ishah v'chiyav b'ven
u'vat. מה כשחייב באיש ואישה לא חילקת בו בין תם למועד. ma
k'shechiyav b'ish v'ishah lo chilakta bo bein tam l'muad. The same way
when the Torah went out of its way don't treat different a
man and a woman, it was way at the beginning of that
whole פרשה parsha to say that that's true whether it's a תם
tam or מועד. muad. Okay. אף כשחייב בבן ובת לא תחלוק בו
בין תם למועד. af k'shechiyav b'ven u'vat lo tachlok bo bein tam
l'muad. So similarly here, when the Torah goes out of its way
to say it's the same הלכה, halacha, right? כמשפט הזה יעשה לו.
k'mishpat hazeh ye'aseh lo. I mean, it's actually explicitly saying same הלכה.
halacha. So if it's making point it's same הלכה halacha by a
child, you should assume same הלכה halacha by a תם tam and
same
הלכה halacha by a מועד. muad. The same way man and woman,
same הלכה halacha by a תם, tam, same הלכה halacha by an
adult. Okay. ועוד קל וחומר. v'od kal vachomer. It's a קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. This will be interesting. What's the קל וחומר? kal vachomer?
מה איש ואישה שכן ריבה כחן בנזיקין לא חילקת בו בין תם
למועד. ma ish v'ishah shekein ribah kochan binzikin lo chilakta bo bein
tam l'muad. We're going to go again and look at the question
of being the perpetrator rather than the victim. By a man and
a woman, they are both fully liable if they cause damage. Okay.
And therefore there is no and no distinction when they are the
victims. Okay. So they have a disadvantaged sort of treatment in
the world of damages because they're actually liable for their damages. Okay.
That's a man and a woman. לא חילקת בין תם למועד. lo
chilakta bein tam l'muad. בן ובת שיפה כחן בנזיקין, ben u'vat sheyifa
kochan binzikin,
children that have a privileged position in the world of damages. Why
do children have a privileged position? They never have to pay for
what they do. They're not yet בר חיובא. bar chiyuva. Okay. Your
kid goes ahead and breaks something under בר או בת מצוה, bar
o bat mitzvah, the kid doesn't pay because he's not בר מצוה.
bar mitzvah. And you don't pay because it's not ממונא דמזיק. mamonah
demazik. Okay. So that's pretty interesting. Like you could say you're negligent,
you're whatever. Yeah, but that's the whole חידוש chiddush of this בבא
קמא. Bava Kamma. If it's just because I was sort of negligent
and indirectly caused and could have prevented, that's not enough. If I
don't directly break it, or my property or my fire doesn't destroy
it, or you don't fall into my pit, then I don't pay.
So my kids aren't my property. The גמרא Gemara even said before,
even if my slave breaks something, and my slave is my property,
I don't pay for it, because it was the act of another
like, you know,
free agent. Okay. So it's actually quite interesting. According to הלכה, halacha,
you are not liable if your kids go and break somebody else's
property. Okay, now once they become בר ובת מצוה, Bar and Bat
Mitzvah, they're liable. And there's actually a later גמרא Gemara that we're
going to see that when, based on a רש"י Rashi and whatever
the רש"י Rashi is then discussed in later ראשונים, Rishonim, that it
could be that when the kid breaks something, he or she is
liable when they become adults, maybe not liable in the court, but
at least has some type of a moral liability when they become
adults.
But interestingly, need to pay for the damage once they become an
adult? Yeah, yeah.
At least a moral liability. But interestingly, the parents are not liable.
Now somebody showed me yesterday that there's a story in the name
of the Rav, that was in the name of the חזון איש,
Chazon Ish, where kid, the case was that a kid threw a
stone into a window and his mother was with him in the
street and broke the window, and they took this case to a
rabbi. The rabbi said, well, you know, the parents are liable. Someone
said, what do you mean the parents are liable? It says, you
know, that, you know, that kids are פטור patur when they do
damage. So they took it to the חזון איש, Chazon Ish, and
the חזון איש Chazon Ish said, well, the kids are פטור patur
if the parents aren't around. But if the parents are around, then
the parents are חייב. chayav. Now, like this story did not give
any logical explanation and, you know, so somebody said, what's this based
on? So I said to me, presumably what it's based on is
some assumption of like this הלכה Halacha which we're going to see
later of דינא דגרמי, Dina D'Garmi, which is like even though indirect
causation you're פטור patur from, the rabbis created a certain subset of
that, which is you have a high degree of the causation is,
it's not a direct act, but it's not totally indirect, and you
have a high degree of responsibility. So some subset of גרמא gerama
they actually did make you pay for. So it seems like the
חזון איש Chazon Ish was understanding if you were there and your
kid was on your watch and you could have stopped him, then
it's like you did it indirectly. But if you're of course you
could say you're more liable, you're more negligent when you let your
kids run around wild and you're not there. But anyway, but this
is really a fascinating הלכה Halacha that the kids aren't חייב, chayav,
and technically speaking, the parents aren't חייב, chayav, it's not ממון המזיק.
mamon ha-mazik. Yes.
Am I missing something? You said if my cow walks into a
shop and it knocks over,
yep, bull in a china shop. You're חייב. chayav. ממון המזיק. mamon
ha-mazik. Exactly. So if my ten-year-old goes, your kids aren't your property.
You're not
חייב. chayav. Correct. That you need the, you need the structure of
ארבעה אבות נזיקין. Arba Avot Nezikin. The fact that you had some
negligence, abstract negligence is not enough. Now, and the other thing is
your slave, so there's a basis, and that's a גמרא Gemara we
learned way at the beginning, that said you were still פטור patur
in that case, because what, your slave can go ahead and cause
a million dollars of damage and you would be liable? So some
understood that that was just to protect you against a vindictive slave,
but others explain it means a different point. You, we can never
make a different person liable for one person's acts. The agent is
the primary person is- you know, we cannot re- the primary person
responsible for their acts is the one who is doing it. If
you can't collect from that person because they're underaged, they're a slave
or whatever, that's your tough luck. Right. So like אין שליח לדבר
עבירה. ein shaliach l'dvar aveirah. But fundamentally, you cannot assign somebody else's
acts, you know, the act fundamentally rests with the agent that performs
it. Anyway, okay. So by a child it has a privileged position
in the world of damages, we'll never pay for damage they do.
So שיפה כח בנזיקין she-yafeh koach be-nezikin לא קל וחומר בתם ומועד.
lo kal va-chomer be-tam ve-muad. I'm sorry. אינו דין שלא תחלוק בהן
בין תם למועד? Eino din she-lo tachalok ba-hen bein tam le-muad? Certainly
you should not distinguish. So they have a privileged position, you should
certainly say that they are- deserved compensation, whether the ox- or whether
the ox is- you know, it's just as weighty when the ox
gores whether the ox is a תם tam or a מועד. muad.
So that's why- why we should be able to learn it out
just logically. אמרת וכי דנין קל וחומר מהחמור
להחמיר? Amarta v'chi danin kal vachomer meichamur l'hachmir? You make a קל
וחומר kal vachomer from the stringent case to be strict? Now what
does this mean? Not very clear at all. Long רש\"י. Rashi. Basically
the way רש\"י Rashi explains it is the following: קל וחומר kal
vachomer is, I will say, if this הלכה Halacha applies in this
more lenient case, it should certainly apply in this more weighty case.
But here what you sort of are saying that, if it applies
by men and women who are seeing more lenient in the sense
that they have a disadvantaged position, it should certainly apply by children
who have a weight- who are advantaged and are maybe a weightier
position. But really what we're saying is, if this הלכה Halacha applies
by a מועד, muad, it should also apply by a תם. tam.
So even though we're trying to use a קל וחומר kal vachomer
to move from מועד muad to תם, tam, we're still moving from
a weightier area of הלכה Halacha to a lighter area of הלכה.
Halacha. So the גמרא Gemara is saying you can't really do that.
Yes, I understand you made an analogy to men and women, you
made a קל וחומר kal vachomer with men and women, but at
the end of the day you're moving from a מועד muad to
a תם tam and you're not allowed to move from the weightier
case to the lighter case. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא ela
so rather we'll say the following. אם אמרת
באיש ואשה שכן חייבין במצות Im amarta b'ish v'ishah sheken chayavin b'mitzvot
and here's another case. Like the קושיא koshya says one challenger or
two challengers. We'll read this as a second challenge. And secondly, maybe
we're weightier by men and women. You said men and women are
lighter because they have a disadvantaged position. That might be true, but
Let's face it, adult men and women generally are given more weight
in הלכה Halacha than children. Okay, אימא אמרת באיש ואשה שכן חייבים
במצוות. Ima amarta be'ish ve'ishah sheken chayavim be'mitzvot. They're obligated in מצוות,
Mitzvot, so obviously they would be treated more
weightily. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar, או בן יגח או בת יגח. o
ben yigach o vat yigach, נגיחה בתם נגיחה במועד נגיחה למיתה נגיחה
לנזיקין. Negicha be'tam negicha be'muad negicha le'misa negicha le'nezikin. So it says
a
lot of the times the word נגיחה. Negicha. It could have said
או בן או בת יגח. o ben o bat yigach. Why does
it say או בן
יגח או בת יגח? o ben yigach o bat yigach?
The extra times it says to gore is to tell you don't
distinguish.
So then he would have said, you know what's going to happen?
They'll say oh you've got to gore או בן או בת.
o ben o bat. I don't know what to tell you. I
don't know what to say. It could have said או בן או
בת יגח, o ben o bat yigach, okay, so the fact that
it says the word יגח yigach twice tells you don't distinguish between
the types of gorings since we've made the point that it's true
when it's a מועד, Muad, it would also be true when it's
a תם. Tam. If it's true by killing, it would be true
by inflicting injury. Okay, it does not matter in any הלכות Halachot
whether the injured party, whether the victim, is an adult or a
minor, same הלכה, Halacha, תם מועד מיתה נזיקין. Tam Muad Misa Nezikin.
Very good. We are now done with דארשינג darshing those פסוקים pesukim
and we get back to—that was like a whole thing basically the
דרשה drasha of these פסוקים pesukim and now we're going to go
back to more general הלכה. Halacha. Yes.
And I don't think I explained my earlier question as well because
we moved on for a second, because if they, on דף מ"ד
עמוד א', daf mem daled amud aleph, started with the מחלוקת machloket
of רבי שמעון ורבי אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon v'Rabbi Eliezer, and he just
said oh one of them held that כופר כפרה היא, kofer kapara
hee, that means everyone else is really holding it's not, right? But
then the גמרא'ס Gemara's position seems to shift that it is.
No, the גמרא'ס Gemara's basic assumption is כופר כפרה. kofer kapara. It's
willing to entertain the possibility that somebody could hold something else in
order to explain a difficult position, to explore positions, but its default
assumption is כופר כפרה. kofer kapara. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this: שור, Shor, new משנה. mishna. So we had this whole
discussion of coupling כפרה kapara with סקילה, skilah, now when the שור
שלא בכוונה shor shelo bekavana case, now we're actually going to start
to look at the שור שלא בכוונה shor shelo bekavana case, which
we've now well established you don't stone the ox, and the only
question is do you pay כופר. kofer. So let's take a look.
שור שהיה מתחכך בכותל. Shor shehayah mitchakech bechotel. An ox was rubbing
against the wall, scratching itself against the wall. It's like the joke,
like you know, like what happens, you know, what time is it
when an elephant sits on a fence? Time to buy a new
fence, right? So what time is it when your ox gores against
the wall? Time to stone the ox. Okay. Your ox is scratching
against the wall, ונפל על אדם, venafal al adam, and you know,
it's a ox against the wall, so the wall falls on somebody
and kills him. Okay, so completely incidental. או נתכוין להרוג את הבהמה
והרג את האדם. o niskaven laharog et habeheima veharog et ha'adam. Or
let's say it was more intentional.
It was trying to kill, but it was trying to kill an
animal and it killed a person. או לכנעני והרג בן ישראל. o
l'Canaani veharog ben Yisrael. Now
I've already warned you about this word כנעני. Canaani. It was trying
to kill a Canaanite and it killed a
Jew. או לנפלים והרג בן קיימא. o linphalim veharog ben kayama. Or
trying to kill a
fetus or child let's say that was within the first 30 days
and was not yet sort of had, you know, could be established
yet as viable.
Is נפלים nephalim a fetus?
It could mean, yeah, but it's here clearly, I mean it doesn't
mean it's goring a—here it probably means a born infant that has
not yet established its viability. והרג בן קיימא, veharog ben kayama, and
established a child that's already viable. פטור Patur in all those cases.
It is exempt from סקילה. skilah. But could it—clearly the clear emphasis
here is סקילה. skilah. Remember the שור האיצטדין shor ha'itzatdin we said
was פטור patur in סקילה. skilah. The emphasis was סקילה, skilah, right?
And so now, the reason for all this is מיתת הבעל כמיתת
השור. mitat habaal kemitat hashor. None of these cases would be executed
in court if as an act of murder, would not have the
death penalty. Okay, certainly not incidental, certainly not trying to kill something
other than a human and accidentally killing a human. That might be
manslaughter but it would not be murder. Okay. Trying to kill a
not viable fetus would not be—only if—right? Or killing a טרפה treifah
and would not be—it's only murder if you try to kill a
viable, non-טרפה treifah person. Of course the most problematic here is the
killing of a
non-Jew. The original text of course was not נכרי Nochri but was
גוי, Goi, but it was changed to נכרי. Nochri. I mean not
כנעני, Canaani, it was גוי. Goi. But obviously that's very, you know,
challenging and uncomfortable, especially if non-Jews are—I mean it's uncomfortable, deeply challenging
and uncomfortable morally and ethically, but in the Middle Ages it was
particularly dangerous if non-Jews might have read it, so it was changed
to כנעני. Canaani. And if that weren't enough, if you look there's
an asterisk and the asterisk at the bottom also tries to tone
it down a bit and say דאינהו הוו פטירי בדיניהו d'innu havu
petiri bidinaihu because they, meaning non-Jews or Canaanites if we want to
go with that, whatever, anyway would exempt if you tried to kill
one person and killed another person. So therefore here too... This ox
is exempt if it tried to kill one person and killed another.
Of course, that's not what the משנה Mishna says, right? The משנה
Mishna doesn't say if it tried to kill ראובן Reuven and killed
שמעון, Shimon, it's exempt. What's the story about that? Somebody tried to
murder ראובן Reuven and murdered שמעון. Shimon. Is that considered an act
of murder? So that's a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. This משנה Mishna
assumes that that would be an act of murder and you would
kill, you'd execute a person and therefore you'd execute the ox. The
only case it's exempt is if the act was trying to be
done, the act that was intended was not an act that would
have been liable for the death penalty. Okay, and included in this
is the act of killing a non-Jew. So the footnote tries to
say, well, it's not that non-Jews are less important, it's just we're
applying their law. And their law would have been if you tried
to kill ראובן Reuven and killed שמעון Shimon you'd be exempt. So
when they're the ones that
killed, we apply their law. Anyway, all of this is to soften
a very harsh גמרא. Gemara. I should say though, the way and
this is really important,
okay, fine, you don't execute a in the case where a non-Jew
is murdered. What does that mean that you are still transgress like
לא תרצח? Lo Tirzach? Is it just some exemption of the particular
capital punishment? Which, okay, would not, you would still not be fully
satisfactory. I mean, the פסוק Pasuk says שופך דם האדם באדם דמו
ישפך, Shofech dam ha'adam ba'adam damo yishafach, which is pretty universal and
talks about executing the one who commits murder and doesn't distinguish, it's
אדם באדם דמו ישפך. Adam ba'adam damo yishafach. So even to distinguish
in the court-imposed punishment would be not still be discomforting and deeply
troubling. But it would at least be saying it's not the same
as saying that we don't consider it to be an act of
murder. So actually, there are some Tannaitic sources and actually the ספר
החינוך Sefer HaChinuch and others that say very explicitly that it is
the biblical act of murder. It's just an exemption from a court-imposed
execution. But what is troubling is רמב"ם. Rambam. רמב"ם Rambam says that
the רמב"ם Rambam is basically, let me read you the text. לא
תרצח Lo Tirzach doesn't apply?
Well, yeah, the language of the רמב"ם Rambam is,
first פרק א הלכה א, Perek Aleph Halacha Aleph, כל הורג נפש.
Kol horeg nefesh. Now, here's the question about again what's printed and
what the manuscript said. The manuscript says, כל הורג נפש בישראל עובר
בלא תעשה שנאמר לא תרצח. Kol horeg nefesh b'Yisrael over b'lo ta'aseh
shene'emar Lo Tirzach.
The printed version says, כל הורג נפש בן אדם עובר בלא תעשה
שנאמר לא תרצח. Kol horeg nefesh ben adam over b'lo ta'aseh shene'emar
Lo Tirzach. Okay, so anyway, that is obviously that is very, obviously
now you have to understand, this took place in a context in
which of course the non-Jews
were oppressive and murderous and whatever, that's certainly how they were perceived
by the rabbis. But anyway, but it's still very different saying that
they don't get, that doesn't have the same court-imposed punishment to say
that it's not seen as fundamentally as murder.
Yes, he also inferred here against abortion because חבלן נפשים Havlan Nefashim
you're פטור, patur, so it's considered,
yeah,
well that we know clearly, yes. And so clearly would include a
case of say goring a woman and we actually discussed that before
about a שור, Shor, doesn't even pay דמי ולדות d'mei vladdot and
so on.
But you mean for a person it does?
Because if it says, yes, and that is true, yes. And we
know that elsewhere, yes.
There is basically an opinion that if somebody killed the wrong person,
they would still be held,
that's what this משנה Mishna sounds like. The only distinction it makes
is between when the intended victim was not something that you would
be executed for, was not a person that you'd be executed for.
It was an animal, it was a fetus, it was a non-Jew.
If the intended victim was somebody you would be executed for, if
you tried to kill ראובן Reuven and you killed שמעון, Shimon, right?
Then the implication is that the שור Shor would get סקילה skila
and that a person would get executed and that is definitely the
standard, there's a debate, but that's the standard position.
But doesn't there need to be a witness
who warns the person?
I see you're trying to kill ראובן Reuven and I say, I
see you're about to commit murder, don't commit murder,
it's a capital
offense. And you say, I don't care, whatever, you go ahead and
you do it and it turns out that you killed the wrong
person, you still been warned that you were about to do an
act of murder. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
אמר
שמואל. Amar Shmuel.
If he just said don't kill so-and-so,
that's an interesting question, like can over-specificity in the warning exempt you?
And there is some discussion about that. I'm not sure,
whatever, yes. So, אמר שמואל פטור מסקילה וחייב בכופר. Amar Shmuel patur
miskila v'chayav b'kofer. Fine, all these cases you're exempt from stoning but
you still pay כופר. kofer. Like we just got through saying according
to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, according to a whole series that you
pay כופר kofer even though you don't stone the שור. Shor. ורבא
אמר פטור מזה ומזה. V'Rava amar patur mizeh umizeh. They're exempt from
both. רבא Rava adopts the position that כופר kofer is linked to
סקילה. skila. So we never get out of this discussion, is כופר
kofer linked to סקילה skila or not? Okay, so that's how they're
debating here. Clearly the משנה Mishna means you're exempt from סקילה, skila,
do we also assume you're exempt from כופר? kofer? So now the
גמרא Gemara says like
this: ואמאי, V'amai, even if you say that כופר kofer is not
linked to סקילה, skila, what is your case שמואל Shmuel that you're
paying כופר? kofer? What type of an animal pays כופר? kofer?
Under what circumstances do you pay כופר? kofer? If the animal is
a מועד. muad. Okay, so what is
the
case? Where's your scenario of כופר? kofer? התם הוא? hatam hu? Presumably
it's rubbing against a wall and the wall collapses on somebody, it's
a תם. tam. גמרא Gemara says כדאמר רב במועד ליפול על בני
אדם בבור. k'd'amar Rav b'muad lipol al bnei adam b'bor. Like רב
Rav later said that an ox was leaning over and there's a
case about an ox falling on a well and killing a person
and that you pay כופר. kofer. And the question was, where is
the, how is it a מועד? muad? So רב Rav said well,
it has a habit of leaning over into wells and trying to
eat the vegetation off the side of the walls of the wells
and being a klutz and slipping and falling on people. So it
actually became a מועד muad for doing that. הכא נמי, hacha nami,
here too במועד להתחכך על בני אדם בכותלים. b'muad l'hitchakech al bnei
adam b'kotlim. It's a מועד muad to rub up against walls and
to kill people in the process. And you warned the owner three
times that your animal has this propensity of scratching itself against walls
and you know, it gets carried away and doesn't know what it's
doing. Now by the way, תוספות Tosafot says that we do not
mean what I just said. We do not mean that it did
it three times and the owner was warned three times about that
because תוספות Tosafot would actually because תוספות Tosafot says you don't need
that. If it's basically just rubbing up against a wall, what type
of an act do we call that normally?
What it does.
Yeah, but what would you call that? קרן שן ורגל. keren shein
va'regel.
שן, shein, it's trying to get benefit. Okay, is a שן תם
או מועד? shein tam o muad? A שן shein is a מועד.
muad. So תוספות Tosafot says what the גמרא Gemara really means is,
although it's a hard read in the גמרא, Gemara, since it is
not doing an intentional act of נזק, nezek, it doesn't need to
go through a process of being warned three times.
תם tam and נזק, nezek, תם tam and מועד muad are only
קרן.
keren. Right, since this is doing an act of getting benefit, this
is שן shein and שן shein is a מועד muad to begin
with. It doesn't sound like that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying
but that's what תוספות Tosafot says the גמרא Gemara is saying, okay?
So let's take a look. Hard read, don't you think? Well, it's
a good logic, I don't know if it's a good read of
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Wait a minute. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. אי
הכי ei hachi says the גמרא Gemara בר קטלא הוא. bar katla
hu. So if that's true
then it's wait a minute, it should be stoned, of course oh
right, why does it not get stoned? If the גמרא Gemara assumes
that if it's doing it three times if it's even either warned
three times or if it's doing it להנאה l'hana'ah but it knows
what it's doing, maybe even if it's not trying to murder but
as long as it knows what it's doing, right, because you know
here's the point, okay, the point is like this is that you
could say an animal has a propensity to rub up against walls
and knock the walls down. But that doesn't make it a מועד
muad to kill people in that process. Even if for three times
people had to be were next to the wall, that was circumstance,
that wasn't the nature of the animal to kill people by standing
against the wall. So in order to make that the nature of
the animal not just to knock down walls but its nature is
to kill people in the process, presumably it had to know that
people were there. And you're saying the animal has a propensity of
rubbing up against walls when people are around and making it fall
on people. Okay, that would be your case of making it a
מועד. muad. Okay, but if that's true then essentially it knows what
it's doing and it's trying to kill the people and that should
make it get סקילה. skila. And so the גמרא Gemara says אי
הכי בר קטלא הוא. ei hachi bar katla hu.
So if it knows what it's doing then it should be then
it should get stoned. בשלמא התם דחזייא ירוקא ונפל. bishlama hatam d'chazya
yaroka v'nafal.
In the case of going falling on people in the pit, you
could say it knows that there are people there but it's too
interested in eating the vegetation on the wall of the pit. So
it could sort of be a מועד muad to do it when
people are in the pit and disregard people in the pit but
not try to kill the people. So therefore it doesn't get its
שן shein and whatever and therefore it wouldn't get stoned. אלא הכא,
ela hacha, but here that you're saying it doesn't get stoned but
it's going to but it's going to pay כופר kofer it's a
מועד, muad, הכא מאי איכא למימר? hacha mai ika l'meimar?
So here if it's rubbing against the wall and it sees people
there, we should presume and it's killing people in the process, we
should presume that means that it's trying to kill people. So it
should get סקילה. skila. And so the גמרא Gemara says no, הכא
נמי במתכוין לכותל
להנאתו. hacha nami b'mitchavein l'kotel l'hana'ato. No no it's not rubbing up
against the wall for the sake of knocking it down. If that
were true and it knew people were there if it were just
trying to knock it down, you're right that would be קרן keren
and then you'd be getting and you'd stone it. But here
it's rubbing up against the wall to scratch its back. I sort
of said that initially. To scratch its back. And therefore the people
are being killed it's only incidental. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
ומנא ידעינן u'mena yadeinan how do you know that it's not trying
to kill the people? Because again we're presuming it knows the people
are there. דבתר דנפל קמחכך ביה d'vatar d'nafal ka m'chachech bei because
even after. Because even after it fell down it kept on rubbing,
scratching itself against the wall. So clearly its goal wasn't to kill
the people, you could clearly tell what it was doing was it
was trying to scratch its back, which makes sense. So basically what
the גמרא Gemara is saying is like this. I'm bracketing תוספות. Tosafot.
תוספות Tosafot is not פשט pshat of the גמרא. Gemara. He tries
to say this whole thing is just שן ורגל shen ve'regel and
therefore automatically it's מועד. muad. The גמרא Gemara sounds like you have
to have proved it habitual. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute.
To prove it habitual, not just to scratch against a wall or
to fall into pits, to prove that it's a klutz or that
has scratches on its back. But to prove that it's habitual to
kill people in the process, you have to prove that it does
this thing even when it knows that people are around.
Well doesn't that make it a קרן? keren? Like it's trying to
kill the people? And the גמרא Gemara could say no. It could
make it gross negligent but it doesn't make it קרן. keren. It
goes for the vegetation even when people are in the pit. But
it's still not trying to kill the person. It scratches up against
the wall even if somebody is right by the wall. But it's
not trying to kill the person, it's just trying to scratch against
the wall. So therefore you don't stone it, but it is a
מועד muad because it has proven that it does these acts regardless
of people's presence and it does these acts in a habitual way
that causes the death of people even when knowing when people are
around. Okay, so therefore you would pay the כופר kofer if it
did it three times, but you would not stone the animal. And
again according to תוספות Tosafot you don't even need three times. תוספות
Tosafot says the basic answer of the גמרא Gemara is that this
is just a case of שן shen and therefore it's automatically a
מועד. muad. נפקא מינה Nafka mina of all this by the way
would be רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. As soon as you say that
this is a שן, shen, then presumably you're only going to be
paying כופר kofer in רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. If you say that
it don't emphasize the שן shen aspect of this, okay then that
wouldn't matter. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues. והא קאתי Ve'ha katti
talking about שן, shen, והא קאתי צרורות נינהו? ve'ha katti tzerorot ninhu?
I don't get it says the גמרא. Gemara. It knocks down the
wall and the stones go and crush somebody, that's not the direct
body of the animal itself. When have you ever had a case
of כופר kofer where you are where it's done by like an
animal kicks a rock and kills somebody? It's normally directly gored by
the animal.
And that's only because up until now we've considered the act as
an act of קרן. keren. Right.
So now that's a good point. There's a huge difference between צרורות
שלא בכוונה tzerorot shelo bekavana and צרורות בכוונה. tzerorot bekavana. Right. If
I if the animal let's say what would you think the הלכה
halacha would be? Let's say the animal was smart, right, because it's
not limited to ox, let's say it's an ape, okay, or whatever.
You get my ape real angry and my ape takes stones and
throws it at somebody and tries to kill them and succeeds in
killing them. Or an ox, I don't know, kicks a big stone,
you know, whatever, kicks pushes down a wall intentionally to kill somebody
by pushing down a wall. Do you think it should take כופר,
kofer, it would get סקילה skilah and pay כופר? kofer? I would
assume yes, okay, because that's actually consciously using it, it's כוחו כגופו.
kocho kegufo.
Unintended כוח, koach, incidental כוח koach is much less כגופו kegufo than
intended כוח. koach. So I don't know, maybe in that case it
would pay. Although רש"י Rashi says no, the גמרא'ס Gemara's assumption is
that you only pay with the body of the animal. But who
knows? If it was an intended כוח, koach, maybe you would. But
צרורות tzerorot is an unintended כוח, koach, an incidental כוח. koach. So
therefore when I accidentally when I rub a wall and it goes
and it rolls, you cannot call what's happened you say I caused
what happened but you can't say that I did what happened. That's
the whole point of צרורות. tzerorot. Unintended כוח koach is much less
כגופו. kegufo. Okay, so where do you ever see that you would
do סקילה skilah and כופר kofer in a case of צרורות? tzerorot?
So אמר רב מרי בריה דרב כהנא amar Rav Mari brei deRav
Kahana דקאזיל מיניה מיניה. dekaza minei minei. It keeps on rubbing against
the stone as the stone is rolling down and basically the idea
the way one of the מפרשים meforshim explain it is basically it's
like the stone is on top of the person and it is
still rubbing against the stone. So it still is directly putting the
pressure of its body, it's like
holding a stick and hitting somebody. That's not כוח. koach. When it
is directly in contact with the body, the body is pushing the
stone which is directly
on top of the person and pushing down on him, that's seen
as גופו, gufo, that's not seen as כוח. koach. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. תניא כוותיה דשמואל ותיובתא דרב. Tanya
kevatei deShmuel utiyuvta deRav. We taught like Shmuel and it's a challenge
on Rav. And this again goes back to this whole point,
can you have כופר kofer without סקילה? skilah? And Shmuel says yes
and that's been the assumption until now, שלושה sheloshah may have had
it different but the assumption is כופר kofer without סקילה skilah yes.
And we have a ברייתא baraita like this which is a challenge
to Rav.
יש חייב במיתה ובכופר. Yesh chayav bemita ubechofer. Some are חייב chayav
with some cases the animal gets stoned and pays כופר. kofer. ויש
חייב בכופר ופטור מן המיתה. Ve'yesh chayav bechofer upatur min hamita. Sometimes
you pay כופר kofer and you don't get stoned. ויש חייב במיתה
ופטור מן הכופר. Ve'yesh chayav bemita upatur min hachofer. Sometimes you get
stoned and don't pay כופר. kofer. ויש פטור מזה ומזה. Ve'yesh patur
mizeh umizeh. And sometimes you don't do either. Okay, very nice little
ברייתא. baraita. כיצד, Keitzad, how does this work out? מועד בכוונה *Mu'ad
b'kavanah*, if it's a מועד *mu'ad* and it intentionally gored, חייב מיתה
chayav misa, ובכופר *chayav mitah u-b'kofer*. That's the easy case. You get
stoned and pay כופר *kofer*. מועד שלא בכוונה *Mu'ad shelo b'kavanah*, it's
a מועד *mu'ad*, so it's habitual, but if it's like this case,
it's not habitual to do it intentionally. It tries to kill a
בהמה *behemah* and kills an אדם *adam* or whatever it is, okay.
So in that case חייב chayav. בכופר *chai b'kofer* because it's habitual,
you pay כופר *kofer* ופטור מן המיתה *u-patur min hamitah*, but you
don't stone it because it's not like an act of murder, it
wasn't intentional. Okay, תם tam בכוונה *tam b'kavanah*, now if it was
the first time, for first three times, even if it was an
intentional act, חייב chayav במיתה פטור patur. מן הכופר *chayav b'mitah patur
min hakofer*. Then you get stoned, it gets stoned, but it doesn't
pay כופר *kofer*. כופר *Kofer* is only by a מועד *mu'ad*. תם
שלא בכוונה *Tam shelo b'kavanah*, and the first time, and it was
an unintentional act, פטור מזה ומזה *patur mi-zeh u-mi-zeh*, you're exempt from
both. A very nice little right distilled ברייתא *braita* of basically telling
you by מיתה *mitah* what matters is כוונה *kavanah*, and by כופר
*kofer* what matters is מועד *mu'ad*, and you can mix and match
and have all four possibilities. Right?
What about צרורות *tzerorot* though? It's not צרורות *tzerorot*?
No, no, no, we're not doing צרורות *tzerorot*. We're moving on. We've
moved on. Okay, so basically you've got the idea of for מיתה
*mitah* what matters is כוונה *kavanah*, כוונה *kavanah* and no כוונה *kavanah*.
And by כופר *kofer* what matters is מועד *mu'ad*, right?
מועד *Mu'ad* versus תם *tam*. So you have all four possibilities. If
it's מועד בכוונה *mu'ad b'kavanah*, it's מיתה *mitah* and כופר *kofer*. Okay.
If it's תם ובכוונה *tam u-b'kavanah*, so because it's תם *tam*, it's
going to be no כופר *kofer*. כופר *Kofer*, no כופר *kofer*. Right?
מיתה
*Mitah*,
no מיתה *mitah*.
Right? So if it's going to be תם *tam*, it's going to
be no כופר *kofer* and yes מיתה *mitah*, right? If it's going
to be no כוונה *kavanah* and מועד *mu'ad*, right, then it's going
to be no מיתה *mitah* and yes כופר *kofer*. I mean, you
can do the rest. Okay. Anyway, basically it's just saying by כופר
*kofer* what matters is תם *tam* and מועד *mu'ad*, by מיתה *mitah*
what matters is כוונה *kavanah* and no כוונה *kavanah*. Fill out your
chart, and you have all four possibilities. Anyway, what does this show
you? This shows you at least going to this ברייתא *braita* clearly
decides one side of the debate that's been with us now for
three days, or two days at least, which is that כופר *kofer*
and מיתה *mitah* are not linked. That you can pay כופר *kofer*
without paying מיתה *mitah*, without doing מיתה *mitah*. With שלא בכוונה *shelo
b'kavanah* and it's a מועד *mu'ad*, you pay כופר *kofer* even though
there's no מיתה *mitah*. Okay. Very good. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
continues. Okay, so נזיקין שלא בכוונה *nezikin shelo b'kavanah*. Now the ברייתא
*braita* continues. What about if it does damage שלא בכוונה *shelo b'kavanah*?
Now you would tell me damage שלא בכוונה *shelo b'kavanah*, wait a
minute, we have a word for that. It's called שן ורגל *shen
v'regel*. Okay, so this means is not that. What this means is,
is our משנה *mishnah*'s case of שלא בכוונה *shelo b'kavanah*. It tried
to גור *gore* a animal and not to kill it, to injure
it, and it gored a human being and it injured him. Or
tried to kill one animal, I don't know, and injured one animal
and injured another. Okay. Would you in that case pay damages? So
of course the intuition is of course yes. But I'm going to
ask you, what are you paying damages for? For what type of
a category? Is it שן ורגל *shen v'regel*? No. Is it קרן
*keren*? Well, it is כוונה להזיק *kavanah l'hazik*, but it wasn't מכוון
להזיק *m'khaven l'hazik* the thing that it was מזיק *mazik*. So obviously
intuitively we would say why should that matter. Okay, but nevertheless that's
the case that we haven't dealt with yet. A case where he's
מכוון להזיק *m'khaven l'hazik* but it was מזיק *mazik* not the thing
that it intended to. Are you going to pay? So let's take
a look. Okay, we know that you're פטור *patur* in מיתה *mitah*
in that case, okay, and you're חייב *chayav* in כופר *kofer*. So
should נזק *nezek* be in the מיתה *mitah* category or in the
כופר *kofer* category? I would of course say it should be in
the כופר *kofer* category, right? מיתה *Mitah* is the very narrow category
that makes it like an act of רציחה *retzichah*. Everything else focuses
on the fact that there was a lost life, there was a
person injured, so of course you should be paying. Who cares that
it injured the thing that it something else that it was trying
to injure? Let's take a look. Okay. ונזיקין שלא בכוונה רבי יהודה
מחייב רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon פוטר *V'nezikin shelo b'kavanah Rabbi Yehuda m'chayiv
Rabbi Shimon potur*. רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says you're חייב *chayav* and
רבי שמעון Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon* says you're פטור *patur*. מאי טעמא דרבי
יהודה *Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Yehuda*? יליף מכופר מכופר *Yalif mi-kofer mi-kofer*. He
says just like כופר *kofer*. מה כופר שלא בכוונה חייב אף נזיקין
נמי שלא בכוונה חייב *Mah kofer shelo b'kavanah chayav af nezikin nami
shelo b'kavanah chayav*. The same way כופר *kofer* you're חייב *chayav* even
though it gored the wrong thing, by נזיקין *nezikin* also. רבי שמעון
Shimon. יליף מקטלי דתורא *Rabbi Shimon yalif mi-katlei d'tora*. He learns it
out from stoning the ox. מה קטלי שלא בכוונה פטור *Mah katlei
shelo b'kavanah potur*, the same way you don't stone it if it
killed a different person, אף נזיקין שלא בכוונה פטור *af nezikin shelo
b'kavanah potur*. Even by נזיקין *nezikin* you wouldn't kill it, you wouldn't
make it pay. ורבי יהודה נמי נילף מקטלי *V'Rabbi Yehuda nami neilef
mi-katlei*? Why doesn't he learn out from the stoning? If you don't
stone it you shouldn't pay for damages? No, דנין תשלומין מתשלומין ואין
דנין תשלומין ממיתה *danyin tashlumin mi-tashlumin v'ein danyin tashlumin mi-mitah*. No, you
learn it out from an issue of payment. The question of payment
of the כופר *kofer* is the better model for payment of damages.
Okay, מיתה *mitah* is a very small category. category. It tries to
make it into an act of רציחה *retzicha*. רבי שמעון Shimon, *Rebbi
Shimon* נמי *nami* נילף *neilef* מכופרו *mikofro*? Why doesn't רבי שמעון *Rebbi
Shimon* learn it out from כופר *kofer*? דנין חיובי דשור מחיובי דשור
*danin chiyuvei de-shor mi-chiyuvei de-shor*. No, you look out from, you focus
on things that you focus on that it's the responsibility of the
ox. Now the ox isn't responsible, it's not a somebody that you
like bring to בית דין Beis Din, *Beis Din*, but it means
that you focus on the fact, look at what the ox did.
לפוקי כופר דחיובא דבעלים *lafukei kofer de-chiyuva de-be'alim*, as opposed to כופר
*kofer* which is the obligation of the owner. Now what does that
mean? To what degree is כופר *kofer* the obligation of the owner
more than the damages that my ox does? What?
Well, okay, it could be. So רש"י *Rashi* says what it really
means is, is that it's כופר כפרה *kofer kaphara*. Okay, and since
כופר *kofer* is כפרה *kaphara*, what?
רש"י *Rashi*'s כפרת נפש *kaparas nefesh*.
כפרת נפש *kaparas nefesh*. Well,
it's the נפש *nefesh* of the מזיק *mazik*. It might be paid
with the דמי ניזק *dmei nizak*, but it's the נפש *nefesh* of
the מזיק *mazik*. So רש"י *Rashi* basically says is, you can't learn
out from כופר *kofer*. That's a כפרה *kaphara*, so therefore that might
be a broader category, whereas other types of things are not about
כפרה *kaphara*. Like if somebody died, that's and that's on your conscience,
so you're going to pay in a broader range of situations. But
for damages, maybe that'll be narrower. That seems to be what רש"י
*Rashi* is saying. The גמרא *Gemara*'s language points a little bit in
a different place, which seems to be saying like, if an ox
gores, I basically say like, okay, this ox did damage, somebody's going
to have to pay. Who's the owner of the ox? Let's get
him to pay. Okay, so I focus on the fact that the
ox did the act and now I just have to find the
owner because he's going to be the person who I'm going to
now get to pay. If an ox kills somebody, I don't say,
oh, this ox killed somebody, who's the person that's חייב מיתה *chayav
misa*? Right? Basically what I say is, ראובן Reuven *Reuven*'s ox killed
somebody, ראובן Reuven *Reuven* is liable for that person's death. Like you
don't start by thinking about the fact of there's like a guilt
of death on the ox, where's the person we're going to assign
it to? It's maybe it's similar to what רש"י *Rashi* is saying,
but it seems to me when we're talking about guilt and death,
we directly ask who's the person responsible. When we're talking about damages,
we sort of say, well, the ox damaged these, somebody's got to
pay, let's go find the owner. Anyway, the bottom line is, that's
what the גמרא *Gemara* says, but obviously the logic is, of course
you should be paying. If you pay by שן *shen* and רגל
*regel* and קרן *keren*, of course you should be paying by קרן
*keren* when it tries to gore one thing and it gores another
thing. And that's certainly how רמב"ם *Rambam* rules, okay? So קרן שלא
בכוונה *keren shelo be-kavana* or not, you know, במכוון *bimchuvan* for a
different thing is still going to pay. Now the גמרא *Gemara* continues,
נתכוון להרוג את הבהמה והרג את האדם פטור *niskavern laharog es habehema
veharag es ha'adam patur*. Okay, so thankfully the גמרא *Gemara* skips over
for a moment, it'll get back to it, the case of the
non-Jew. Anyway, tried to kill a בהמה *behema* kills a person you're
פטור *patur*. הא נתכוון להרוג את זה והרג את זה חייב *ha
niskavern laharog es zeh veharag es zeh chayav*. The גמרא *Gemara* makes
the obvious inference from the משנה *Mishnah*. If the משנה *Mishnah* sounds
like tried to kill ראובן Reuven *Reuven* and killed שמעון *Shimon*, you
would stone the ox and presumably you would execute a person, that
would be an act of murder. מתניתין דלא כרבי שמעון *masnisin d'lo
k'Rebbi Shimon*. It's not like רבי שמעון *Rebbi Shimon*. דתניא *d'tanya*, we
saw in a ברייתא *beraisa*, רבי שמעון אומר אפילו נתכוון להרוג את
זה והרג את זה פטור *Rebbi Shimon omer afilu niskavern laharog es
zeh veharag es zeh patur*. That even by a case of a
human being, I mean the assumption here is human and the ox
is the same. Tried to kill ראובן Reuven *Reuven* and killed שמעון
*Shimon* you're פטור *patur*. And the רבנן Rabanan *Rabbanan* disagree, they say
if you tried to kill ראובן *Reuven* and killed שמעון *Shimon* you're
חייב *chayav*. מאי טעמא דרבי שמעון *mai ta'ama d'Rebbi Shimon*, what's the
reason of רבי שמעון *Rebbi Shimon*? דאמר קרא השור יסקל hashor yisakeil,
וגם בעליו יומת *d'amar kra hashor yisakeil vegam ba'alav yumas*. כמיתת בעלים
כך מיתת השור *k'misa'as ba'alim kach misa'as hashor*. Now nobody disagrees with
that. That basically everybody agrees. That the same circumstances in which you
would kill the owner, you kill the ox. מה בעלים עד דמכוין
ליה אף שור shor נמי עד דמכוין ליה *mah ba'alim ad d'michavein
leih af shor nami ad d'michavein leih*. This is רבי שמעון *Rebbi
Shimon*'s חידוש *chiddush*. רבי שמעון *Rebbi Shimon* though says, I hold by
murder that you're only חייב *chayav* if you intend for the particular
victim. And since I hold that by murder, I hold it by
a goring ox. ובעלים גופייהו מנלן *u'ba'alim gufeihu minalan*, and where does
רבי שמעון *Rebbi Shimon* know this, that the in a case of
murder, you have to intend for the particular victim? דאמר קרא וארב
לו וקם עליו *d'amar kra ve'arav lo vekam alav*. He laid in
wait for him and rose up against him. עד שיתכוין לו *ad
she-yiskavein lo*, until he actually had intention for that person, he intended
and planned against plotted against that person. ורבנן *ve-Rabbanan*, now the רבנן
*Rabbanan*, everybody agrees the same thing for the ox is for the
human. The רבנן *Rabbanan* just say for murder, it doesn't matter if
you intended for ראובן *Reuven* and killed שמעון *Shimon*. האי וארב לו
מאי עבדי ליה *hai ve'arav lo mai avdi leih*, so what do
they do with that verse of laying in wait, which sounds like
you have a particular victim, it has to be specific? אמרי דבי
רבי ינאי פרט לזורק אבן לגב *amri devei Rebbi Yanai prat le-zorek
even le-gav*. No, no, you're right. It means if you just threw
a stone into a group of people and had nobody particular in
mind, in that case you'd be exempt. If you tried to kill
ראובן *Reuven* and killed שמעון *Shimon* you're חייב *chayav*, and therefore the
ox is also חייב *chayav*. Okay, but if you tried to kill
throw it in a group and you didn't you wanted to kill
somebody but it didn't matter who, you'd be exempt. Now what difference
does it make? ראובן *Reuven*, שמעון *Shimon*, a group, you're still trying
to kill someone, what difference does it make? So let's see what
the גמרא *Gemara* says. היכי דמי *heichi dami*? What's the case you're
exempt? אילימא דאיכא תשעה כנענים *ileima d'ika tisha knanim*. Okay, again, it's
not כנענים *knanim*. Okay, if there are nine Canaanites, non-Jews, okay, ואחד
ישראל ביניהם *ve-echad Yisrael beineihem*, and one Jew among them... Therefore you're
exempt because we can't say you were trying to kill a Jew
because the majority were non-Jews. So the גמרא says, תיפוק ליה דרובא
כנענים נינהו. teipukei de-rubah kna'anim ninhu. You don't need a פסוק. pasuk.
Obviously we would define your act based on the majority of that
group. And we couldn't characterize your act as trying to kill a
Jew. אי נמי פלגא ופלגא ספק נפשות להקל. Ee nami palga u-palga
safeik nefashot le-hakel. Even if it was half Jews and half non-Jews,
we wouldn't be able to characterize it as an act of intending
to kill a Jew. So you wouldn't need a פסוק. pasuk. אלא
צריכא
דאיכא תשעה ישראלים ואחד כנעני. Ella tzricha de-ika tish'ah yisraelim ve-echad kna'ani.
Okay, the majority are Jews. So without a פסוק pasuk we would
say you threw a stone in a group of people, the majority
of whom were Jews. We will define that you didn't care who
you killed, but we will define it as an act of intending
to kill a Jew. We'll define it by the majority. And therefore
if lo and behold you did kill a Jew, then you'll be
executed for it. That's what we would have said. And comes along
the פסוק pasuk and teaches
you דאף על גב דרובא ישראלים נינהו כיון דאיכא חד כנעני ביניהו
הוי ליה קבוע. de-af al gav de-rubah yisraelim ninhu keivan de-ika chad
kna'ani beneihu hovei leh kavua. He's fixed in his place. וכל קבוע
כמחצה על מחצה דמי. Ve-chol kavua ke-mechetza al mechetza dami. This is
this crazy principle that anytime that there's a doubt, but the question
of doubt is sort of in a fixed place, you treat it
as fifty-fifty. This actually is the source of that הלכה. halacha. Since
the פסוק pasuk is telling you if he threw the stone in
the group and it wound up killing a Jew and the majority
were Jews, since there was one non-Jew there, we can't characterize it
as an act of intending to kill a Jew. We characterize it
as it was a doubtful an act of questionable intent, like he
didn't have a specific intent. He said I'll just, I don't care
who I kill. But so we have to characterize it by the
circumstances. So by the circumstances though, we view it as though it's
equally weighted and we cannot identify characterize it as an act of
trying to kill a Jew. And therefore ספק נפשות להקל safeik nefashot
le-hakel we will not execute him. So that's what they learn. In
that case where it's not clear who the intended victim was, Jew
or non-Jew. But if he tried to kill ראובן and killed שמעון,
they say you would be חייב. Okay? So that debate is between
רבנן and רבי שמעון by are you חייב if you tried to
kill ראובן and killed שמעון. And therefore it's the same with the
debate by murder, it's a debate by this goring ox. In the
process we repeated this whole very difficult גמרא that treats the murder
of a non-Jew different than the murder of a Jew. Yes.
So the difference between ביטול ברוב bitul be-rov and קבוע kavua is
that here we know that there's a non-Jew there? Yeah.
Yeah. You never say ביטול ברוב bitul be-rov when the
question is right nine versus one.
Right.
You know there's a non-Jew. Correct. If it was just it was
a group of people and you didn't know who they were, but
the population, the demographics were that it was a town that was
ninety-nine percent Jewish, that would be that would not be קבוע. kavua.
Okay, because you can't identify.
Exactly. Exactly. Yes. You know, don't you think that the application or
the generating of this principle of מחצה על מחצה mechetza al mechetza
and כל קבוע kol kavua sort of levels or equalizes the life
of the Jew and the life of the non-Jew?
It serves that it serves that hermeneutic function as bizarre as it
might be.
It's interesting. I mean you see what I'm saying? Still doesn't help
for the case of when the non-Jew was killed. It still says
because there was a non-Jew here the act was less weighty. But
I hear the point that in the process you're sort of treating
them. Yeah. It's an interesting yeah, that's an interesting thought. I hear
that. That is an interesting thought. Yes.
Is there some parallel here too to the question of helping a
non-Jew on שבת Shabbat or?
Yeah, I mean those questions are related questions. Absolutely. Absolutely. Yeah. But
here again we're talking about whether it's a capital crime. By the
way, I don't know in secular law. Clearly if in secular law
you tried to kill ראובן and you killed שמעון, you're going to
be sent away for murder. But in states that have the death
penalty, right, which that's what we're dealing here with, not whether is
it murder but is it a death penalty. In states that have
the death penalty, right, normally there needs to be, you know, malice
aforethought and there needs to be whatever, right, it needs to be
like a planned murder. There needs to be like a high level
for capital to execute for capital punishment. What would be if somebody
really was planning to kill ראובן and accidentally killed the wrong person?
Would that be a case of would they execute somebody for that?
I think there was a TV show like that. Really? Yeah where
somebody was he's trying to kill his wife and somebody came down
outside the building and he killed that person. Person was trying to
commit suicide and he killed him by accident.
All right. Anyways, so I don't know what the secular law would
be because here again we're not asking whether it's murder, we're asking
whether you'd get the death penalty.
I just interesting point about whether it also applies to the non-Jew.
No, no. Meaning if we assume that it does apply and the
question is one of death penalty, it's an interesting question, מתכוין להרוג
את זה והרג את זה, mitkavein laharog et zeh ve-harag et zeh,
is that worthy of the death penalty or not? Okay, let's take
a look. Let's try I know we only have a minute but
we can do the next one quickly. I'd like to get to
the bottom of the דף. daf. שור אשה ושור יתומים ושור אפוטרופוס
שור המדבר ושור הקדש שור גר שמת ואין לו יורשים הרי אלו
חייבים מיתה. Shor ishah ve-shor yetomim ve-shor apotropos shor ha-midbar ve-shor hekdesh
shor ger she-met ve-ein lo yorshim harei elu chayavim mitah. If it
was owned by a woman or by orphans, minors, or by the
אפוטרופוס apotropos who was, you know, overseeing the estate of the minors,
or it was ownerless, שור המדבר's shor ha-midbar a wild ox, or
it was owned by the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, or it was
owned It was owned by a convert who died and therefore now
it's ownerless, who has no heirs. All these cases are פטור מן
המיתה, patur min hamisa, I'm sorry, all these cases are חייב מיתה,
it still committed murder, you still stone the ox, doesn't matter who
the owner is. רבי יהודה אומר לא, Rabbi Yehuda omer lo, שור
המדבר
שור הקדש שור שגר שמת, shor hamidbar shor hekdesh shor sheger shemeit,
פטורים מן המיתה. pturim min hamisa. Those three cases when it's ownerless
or owned by the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, it's exempt, לפי שאין
להם בעלים, lefi she'ein lahem be'alim, it does not have owners, or
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash it doesn't have a normal lay owner.
Does okay? Those cases of ownerless or owned by the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, you'd say actually you would not stone the ox. תנו
רבנן, Tanu rabanan,
שור שור שבע. shor shor shiva. It says שור shor seven times
in the parsha. כי יגח שור איש, Ki yigach shor ish, או
נגח איש שור נגח הוא, o nagach איש shor nagach hu, שור
שור שור. shor shor shor. It says שור seven times. Six of
them are extra. So what are the six extra? לאו שור איש
שור יתומים שור אפוטרופוס שור המדבר שור הקדש שור גר שמת ואין
לו יורשים. lav shor ish shor yesomim shor apotropos shor hamidbar shor
hekdesh shor ger shemeit ve'ein lo yorshim. Those are six, okay? רבי
יהודה אומר שור המדבר שור הקדש שור גר שמת שאין לו יורשים
פטורים מן המיתה. Rabbi Yehuda omer shor hamidbar shor hekdesh shor ger
shemeit she'ein lo yorshim pturim min hamisa. No, those last three are
exempt, לפי שאין להם בעלים. lefi she'ein lahem be'alim. You need to
have an owner to get stoned, which is interesting, right? It's partly
maybe the question is how much do you view it as the
ox committed murder and we're going to stone the ox, how much
do you view it as sort of the owner sort of committed
murder through the ox and we're going to stone the ox? Now
of course, the fact that you do it the first three times
when it's a תם and the Torah says בעל השור נקי ba'al
hashor naki seems to be saying we're not focusing on the owner,
we're focusing on the ox. So you certainly understand the position of
the תנא קמא. Tana Kama. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, פוטר
היה רבי יהודה אפילו נגח ולבסוף הקדיש נגח ולבסוף הפקיר. poter haya
Rabbi Yehuda afilu nagach ulevasof hikdish nagach ulevasof hifkir. Rabbi Yehuda would
exempt even if it started with an owner when it killed somebody
and then he donated it to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or
he was מפקיר mafkir it. Then also you wouldn't stone, okay, which
is by the way good idea, if your ox gores and kills
somebody, you're going to lose the ox anyway, might as well make
a donation to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and get a tax
write-off. ממה, Mima, מדקתני תרתי, mide'ktani tarti, since the mishna teaches you
two cases. שור המדבר, Shor hamidbar, a wild ox, ושור הגר שמת
ואין לו יורשים, veshor hager shemeit ve'ein lo yorshim, or owned by
a ger who has no heirs. שור הגר שמת, Shor hager shemeit,
מאי ניהו? mai nihu? What how's that case different? דכיון דאין לו
יורשים, dekivan de'ein lo yorshim, since he has no heirs, הוי ליה
שור הפקר, hei lei shor hefker, it's ownerless. היינו שור המדבר, Hainu
shor hamidbar, that's a wild ox. Why does the mishna have to
give two cases? If a wild ox is the same as a
ger who died. היינו שור גר שמת ואין לו יורשים. Hainu shor
ger shemeit ve'ein lo yorshim. אלא הא קמשמע לן, Ela ha kamashma
lan, it's teaching you דאפילו נגח ולבסוף הקדיש נגח ולבסוף הפקיר. de'afilu
nagach ulevasof hikdish nagach ulevasof hifkir.
It's telling you the reason to give the additional case of a
ger that died is to tell you if it gored and killed
while the ger was alive and then the ger died, then you
also don't stone it according to Rabbi Yehuda. That's why it's different
than a wild ox. A wild ox was never owned, or even
in a case where it was owned and then the ger died,
if right now it's not owned when it comes to be judged
in בית דין, then you're going to get off according to, the
ox will get off according to Rabbi Yehuda. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya
nami hachi, we taught similarly. יתר על כן אמר רבי יהודה אפילו
נגח ולבסוף הקדיש נגח ולבסוף הפקיר פטור. Yesar al ken amar Rabbi
Yehuda afilu nagach ulevasof hikdish nagach ulevasof hifkir patur. Even if first
it killed and then you sanctified, then you were מפקיר mafkir it,
פטור. שנאמר והועד בבעליו ולא ישמרנו והמית איש או אשה. Shene'emar vehu'ad
biva'alav velo yishmerenu veheimit ish o isha. You warn and then it
kills. עד שתהא מיתה ועמידה בדין שוין כאחד. Ad shetehei misa ve'amida
badin shavin ke'echad. It has to kill and you have to then
stand in court and all that has to be in the same
scenario of being owned by an owner. So the gemara says גמר
דין לא בעינן? gemar din lo ba'inan? What do you mean? Why
do you say standing in the court? For it to have its
status of a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, you need to finish the
court case. So והשור יסקל, vehashor yisakeil, when it says השור יסקל,
that's גמר דין הוא, gemar din hu, that's when the judgment was
passed. אלא אימא, Ela eima, fine. עד שתהא מיתה, Ad shetehei misa,
right, it says והמית איש או
אשה, veheimit ish o isha, והועד בבעליו, vehu'ad biva'alav, etc. So ועמידה
בדין וגמר דין שוין כאחד. ve'amida badin vegemar din shavin ke'echad. It
all has to be at once. Now what we did not spell
out, which I need to just take one second before we end,
is where is this idea of owner mattering? Because it does say
the whole parsha is כי יגח שור איש, Ki yigach shor ish,
והועד בבעליו, vehu'ad biva'alav,
presumes it has owners, right? So even though logically what the rabbi
is saying is it doesn't matter if there are owners, it doesn't
matter if the owner is a woman, you don't interpret the word
שור איש shor ish that it's only a man's ox, or it
doesn't matter if the owner is an adult or not. It doesn't
matter even if it has no owners, yes the Torah's talking about
owners, but logically it doesn't matter, you stone the ox regardless. What
Rabbi Yehuda says is I'm sorry, the parsha says והועד בבעליו. vehu'ad
biva'alav. So the parsha is talking about owners and if there are
no owners you're not going to stone the ox and even if
there are no owners at the end of the process, you're not
going to stone the ox because it's all read as one process
and you need to have owners throughout. So that's Rabbi Yehuda's position
but the rabbis of course make a lot more sense. Okay, we
will continue.